<DOC    id="ENG_NW_001278_20131206_F00012UNK">
<DATE_TIME>2013-12-06T16:54:18</DATE_TIME>
<HEADLINE>
Pakistani parliament adjourned to mourn Nelson Mandela's death
</HEADLINE>
<AUTHOR>王玉</AUTHOR>
<TEXT>
Pakistani parliament adjourned to mourn Nelson Mandela's death

Pakistani parliament adjourned to mourn Nelson Mandela's death

ISLAMABAD, Dec. 6 (Xinhua) -- Pakistani parliament was adjourned on Friday to pay homage to South Africa's former President and Nobel Laureate Nelson Rolihlahla Mandela, who died on Thursday at the age of 95.

The National Assembly or Lower House of the parliament did not take up the routine business and the members expressed shock at the demise of Nelson Mandela and lauded his struggle against the apartheid.

The House unanimously adopted a resolution, expressing grief and sorrow over the sad demise of Nelson Mandela.

The resolution, moved by Advisor on Foreign Affairs Sartaj Aziz, said Pakistani people share the pain of South African people over the death of the great leader who is revered as icon of true democracy.

"Pakistan wishes the South African people to bear this irreparable loss with courage and fortitude," the resolution said.

Applauding Mandela's services for democracy and human rights, the National Assembly's resolution said Nelson Mandela was the person who stood for the rights, honor and dignity of oppressed people.

It said Pakistan has been at the forefront to dismantle the apartheid and Nelson Mandela appreciated Pakistan's efforts in this regard.

Nelson Mandela twice visited Pakistan and during his second visit he also addressed the joint sitting of the Parliament.

The resolution said that the great South African leader will continue to live in the hearts and minds of Pakistani people.

While paying tributes to Mandela, leader of the Opposition Syed Khurshid Shah and a senior political leader, Mahmood Khan Achakzai, said the South African leader was a role model for democracy and politics of reconciliation.

They requested the chair to adjourn the proceedings of the House today in honor of the great South African leader.

Minister for Parliamentary Affairs Shaikh Aftab Ahmad also supported the opposition's proposal and said it will send a good message to the democratic forces of the world.

Pr)*bƪ*esident Mamnoon Hussain and Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif have expressed their deep sorrow and grief over the sad demise of former President of South Africa Nelson Mandela.

In their message, they said Nelson Mandela's struggle against discriminatory attitudes in the society is respected worldwide.

Bilawal Bhutto, chairman of the main opposition Pakistan Peoples Party, also paid tributes to the great South African leader and recalled his meeting with his slain mother Benazir Bhutto. He said in a statement the world will remember Mandela for his struggle.

Another senior opposition leader, Imran Khan, also praised Nelson Mandela for opposing violence and the use of force in his life. "I had the privilege to meet him and he named the founder of Pakistan Muhammad Ali Jinnah and the Indian freedom fighter Mahatma Gandhi amongst his inspirations," he said. Enditem
</TEXT>
</DOC>
