<DOC    id="ENG_NW_001278_20130429_F00012I7X">
<DATE_TIME>2013-04-29T16:06:05</DATE_TIME>
<HEADLINE>
Hopes of more survivors diminishing in Bangladesh building collapse
</HEADLINE>
<AUTHOR>Naim</AUTHOR>
<TEXT>
Hopes of more survivors diminishing in Bangladesh building collapse

Hopes of more survivors diminishing in Bangladesh building collapse

DHAKA, April 29 (Xinhua) -- Rescuers with cranes and other heavy equipment began removing huge concrete slabs and chunks of debris Monday morning from the collapsed Dhaka building after fire delayed their efforts Sunday night, virtually giving up hope of finding more trapped survivors.

Six days into the collapse of the eight-storey Bangladesh building that left nearly 400 dead so far, rescuers gave up hope to save any more lives after they failed to rescue a young garment worker named Shahana, who was believed to be the last remaining survivor.

Defying the stench of decaying bodies which filled the air around the ruins of the building Rana Plaza, the rescuers relentlessly worked for four hours to pull out the female worker who was spotted sometime on Sunday.

"But our entire efforts to rescue Shahana went in vain due to a fire that broke out around 10:00 p.m., when a rescuer was cutting a steel bar to pull her out," said Shahinul Islam, director of Bangladesh Army's Inter Services Public Relations (ISPR).

He said the rescuers, at least six of which were injured, had to retreat from the scene of the wreckage where the fire broke out. The fire-fighters managed to bring blaze under control shortly but smokes continued to billow from the burning wreckage scene even on Monday afternoon when a Xinhua correspondent reported from the site.

Somoy television footage showed some rescuers cried, loudly or softly, some are visibly upset, others are outwardly calm as they had left Shahana who was earlier provided with food, water and oxygen.

"Sir, please pull out me, I've a three-year old boy," a teary- eyed rescuer quoted trapped Shahana as saying.

"We don't know what happened to her after the fire incident but we pray for a miracle," said the ISPR spokesman.

Dozens of family members are still keenly awaiting at the disaster site. But there is no specific information about how many people are still missing.

At a press briefingPRA at the disaster site in Savar on the outskirts of capital Dhaka on Sunday morning, Major General Chowdhury Hasan Suhrawardy of Bangladesh Army's 9th Infantry Division announced to deploy cranes and other heavy equipment to expedite rescue operation.

Bangladesh authorities refrained from deploying heavy machinery amid concern that tearing chunks from the building might jeopardize the safety of anyone clinging to life beneath the sandwiched floors of the building, which crumbled like a pack of cards on Wednesday at about 8:30 a.m. local time.

In one of the worst tragedies in Bangladesh since its independence in 1971, officials say rescuers pulled alive over 2, 500 people including several people on Sunday. They say death toll could surpass 400.

Following the cracks which were detected just one day before the accident, the workers were evacuated and the garments authorities declared a leave for Tuesday. But officials of the factories forced the workers on the next morning to join workplaces in the building.

According to sources, almost all the death victims are workers of five factories -- Phantom Apparels, Phantom Tac, Ether Tex, New Wave Style and New Wave Bottoms -- which make clothing for many major global brands.

Six floors of the building housed the five garment factories which, according to BGMEA, employed nearly 3,500 workers, mostly of them women. Furthermore, there were also a bank's branch and hundreds of shops inside.  Enditem
</TEXT>
</DOC>
