<DOC    id="ENG_NW_001278_20131005_F00012XHZ">
<DATE_TIME>2013-10-05T05:08:48</DATE_TIME>
<HEADLINE>
Roundup: Four killed, dozens injured in clashes in Egypt
</HEADLINE>
<AUTHOR>marwa2</AUTHOR>
<TEXT>
Roundup: Four killed, dozens injured in clashes in Egypt

Roundup: Four killed, dozens injured in clashes in Egypt

CAIRO, Oct. 4 (Xinhua) -- Four people were killed and dozens injured in clashes between supporters of ousted president Mohamed Morsi and anti-Morsi residents and security forces in the Egyptian capital of Cairo and other major cities on Friday, state-run Ahram newspaper reported on its website.

Thousands of Muslim Brotherhood (MB)'s supporters flocked to Egypt's main squares after the Friday prayer to protest against the armed forces which they said overthrew Morsi, Egypt's first elected president, in a "coup."

Four people were killed in Cairo which witnessed the fiercest clashes on Friday after deadly August, as Morsi's loyalists clashed with both the local citizens and police when they attempted to enter downtown Tahrir Square, official news agency MENA said.

Police fired tear gas and warning shots to disperse the protesters, while troops sealed off the square with tanks and barbed wire to prevent them from entering it, according to MENA.

A 57-year old man from the Muslim Brotherhood was shot dead on Qaser Aani street, near Tahrir Square, Ahram quoted Sayed Shafiq of the interior ministry as saying. He added that the man joined a group of Islamists who tried to launch sit-in in the square.

The other three victims were killed in fighting between Morsi's loyalists and local residents on Ibn Sinder street in Heliopolis district in Cairo near the presidential palace, Shafiq added.

He added no sit-in will be allowed in any square in Egypt.

Ahram, which quoted another security source, said the Muslim Brotherhood planned to rally in Tahrir Square and outside the headquarters of the defense ministry in Heliopolis district to make them bases for sit-ins.

However, the security forces managed to disperse the protesters to curb violence, the source added.

The protesters chanted slogans against the army and Defense Minister Abdel Fattah al-Sisi who they said led a "coup" in July.

Footage of State TV showed that hundreds of protesters )òcoming out of main mosques after the Friday prayers carried banners with pictures of victims in a crackdown on Morsi's supporters on Aug. 14, vowing to take revenge.

Hundreds of Morsi's supporters took to street in Nasr City district, marching towards the Rabaa al-Adawiya Square, where security forces dismantled a massive protest camp leaving more than 850 dead on that day. They fought with residents in the district, however, security forces managed to halt the fighting.

On Friday evening, hundreds of protesters hurled stones at soldiers guarding the defense ministry, intending to defy the curfew that starts at 7 p.m. (1700 GMT), MENA reported.

Meanwhile, Islamists took to street in Alexandria and Assiut province in upper Egypt to protest against an ongoing crackdown in which nearly 3,500 people have been jailed, according to the Muslim Brotherhood official website.

The top leaders of the Muslim Brotherhood were referred to courts over charges of inciting murder and violence. Morsi himself has been detained incommunicado, and the organization's activities were banned by an Egyptian court last month. The court also ordered to seize the group's assets.

MENA reported that Ahmed Sobieh, the spokesperson of the MB's Freedom and Justice Party, was arrested on Friday over charges of inciting violence and killing anti-Morsi protesters.

Friday's violence came a day after European Union foreign policy chief Catherine Ashton held talks in Cairo with the interim president, defense minister, and two Brotherhood politicians. She urged both sides to pursue reconciliation.

Representative of Ultra-conservative al-Nour party Ashraf Thabet told independent Newspaper al-Masry el-Youm that Ashton failed to convince the Muslim Brotherhood to join the political process or to dispense with their request to reinstate Morsi.

At the same time, some Egyptian activists and movements accused Ashton of meddling in Egyptian affairs.

The Friday demonstrations are held under the call of the National Alliance for Supporting Legitimacy whose members mainly come from the Muslim Brotherhood. It called for continuous protests in Tahrir Square from Friday until Morsi is reinstated.

Meanwhile anti-Morsi groups have called for rallies in Tahrir Square on Sunday on the occasion of 40th anniversary for the Egyptian military's victory over Israel on Oct. 6, 1973. State media and some private networks aired national songs around the clock along with documentaries of the war that glorify the military.   Enditem
</TEXT>
</DOC>
