<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20130903.0115" type="story" from_file="/newswire/daily_process/nyt/english/source_data/20130903/20130903,9f7fbdaec626d2989ffbb26253228ec3.xml">
<HEADLINE>
MICROSOFT TO BUY NOKIA UNITS AND ACQUIRE EXECUTIVE
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
This article is part of TIMES EXPRESS. It is a condensed version of a story that will appear in tomorrow’s New York Times.);
</P>
<P>
SEATTLE - Microsoft said it had reached an agreement to acquire the handset and services business of Nokia for about $7.2 billion, in an audacious effort to transform Microsoft’s business for a mobile era that has largely passed it by.
</P>
<P>
Late Monday, Microsoft and Nokia said 32,000 Nokia employees would join Microsoft as a result of the all-cash deal, which is meant to turn the Finnish mobile phone pioneer into the engine for Microsoft’s mobile efforts.
</P>
<P>
Stephen Elop, the former Microsoft executive who was running Nokia until the deal was signed, will rejoin Microsoft after the transaction closes, setting him up as a potential successor to Steven A. Ballmer, Microsoft’s chief executive. Ballmer has said he will retire from the company within 12 months.
</P>
<P>
“This agreement is really a bold step into the future for Microsoft,” Ballmer said in a telephone interview from Finland. “We’re excited about the talent capabilities it will bring to Microsoft.”
</P>
<P>
The deal, which was first broached between Microsoft and Nokia executives in February, is the latest transformation of the 150-year-old Finnish company. Risto Siilasmaa, Nokia’s interim chief executive, said Tuesday that the sale of the handset business was the logical step in the company’s evolution but still pulled on his heartstrings.
</P>
<P>
“Selling a business is sometimes the right cause of action, but it’s emotionally complicated,” Siilasmaa said.
</P>
<P>
A megadeal between Nokia and Microsoft is something that pundits and analysts have speculated about for years, after Elop joined Nokia and signed a pact with Microsoft in February 2011 to standardize the software company’s Windows Phone operating system. The cellphone fortunes of the two companies have become closely intertwined, but the relationship has done little to turn either company into a leader in the mobile business.
</P>
<P>
Carolina Milanesi, an analyst at Gartner, said she believed the deal could help the companies respond more quickly to the dynamism of the mobile market. “They need to move faster,” she said.
</P>
<P>
By offloading its handset business, Nokia is attempting to reboot itself around its telecommunications equipment unit, NSN, its mapping and location business and an extensive patent portfolio.
</P>
<P>
“Nokia can get rid of the uncertainty of its handset business at a great price,” said Janardan Menon, a telecommunications analyst at Liberum Capital in London. “It’s a good deal for both Microsoft and Nokia.”
</P>
<P>
Shares in Nokia rose 37 percent in trading in Helsinki on Tuesday, while Microsoft shares fell more than 4.5 percent.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
