<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20130702.0103" type="story" from_file="/newswire/daily_process/nyt/english/source_data/20130702/20130702,6dfda6f898482db8ac991693a7b8f051.xml">
<HEADLINE>
SNOWDEN MUST STOP HURTING U.S. TO STAY IN RUSSIA, PUTIN SAYS
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
EDS: SUBS throughout for complete writethru; NEW headline.); (This article is part of TIMES EXPRESS. It is a condensed version of a story that will appear in tomorrow’s New York Times.);
</P>
<P>
MOSCOW -The Kremlin found itself confronted with a dilemma it had hoped to avoid Monday after an official revealed that Edward J. Snowden, the former National Security Agency contractor wanted by the United States, had submitted a request to Russia for political asylum.
</P>
<P>
Kim N. Shevchenko, the consul at Sheremetyevo airport, said that Snowden’s traveling companion hand-delivered Snowden’s request late Sunday evening to a Russian consulate in Terminal F of the airport and that it had been passed to the country’s Foreign Ministry.
</P>
<P>
No high-level officials confirmed the report Monday.
</P>
<P>
Putin has tried to stake out a neutral position since Snowden landed at Sheremetyevo airport eight days ago. If he grants Snowden asylum, Putin will inflict severe damage on Russia’s relationship with the United States. If he plays a part in his capture, he will appear to have bent to Washington’s will.
</P>
<P>
At a news conference on Monday, Putin said Snowden was welcome to stay in Russia as long as he stopped publishing classified documents that hurt the United States’ interests. He went on to acknowledge that this was unlikely to happen.
</P>
<P>
“If he wants to go somewhere and they accept him, please, be my guest,” Putin said. “If he wants to stay here, there is one condition: He must cease his work aimed at inflicting damage to our American partners, as strange as it may sound from my lips.”
</P>
<P>
For the second time, he took pains to say that Snowden had not been recruited by Russian intelligence - an impression that could corrode Snowden’s image as a truth-teller and drive away some supporters.
</P>
<P>
Putin’s spokesman, meanwhile, said as recently as Sunday that Snowden’s case “was not one on the Kremlin’s agenda,” noting that Sheremetyevo’s transit zone is legally not the part of territory of the Russian Federation.
</P>
<P>
Snowden’s application for asylum could make it difficult for the Kremlin to remain neutral, especially since the case has become a primary topic for public discussion in Russia over the last several days.
</P>
<P>
As an international oil and gas forum convened here Monday morning, analysts speculated that Putin and President Nicolás Maduro of Venezuela would use the opportunity to negotiate terms for Snowden to leave the Russian airport.
</P>
<P>
Russia enjoys warm ties with Venezuela, a major arms customer and energy partner, which sees the alliance as a way of countering the United States’ influence in Latin America.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
