<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20130820.0168" type="story" from_file="/newswire/daily_process/nyt/english/source_data/20130820/20130820,d730ec889312526dfa8cbbc365dbe89c.xml">
<HEADLINE>
EGYPTIAN POLICE ARREST SPIRITUAL LEADER OF MUSLIM BROTHERHOOD
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Alan Cowell contributed reporting from London, and Mayy El Sheikh from Cairo.
</P>
<P>
CAIRO - The Egyptian police arrested the spiritual leader of the Muslim Brotherhood early Tuesday, hours after a court ordered the release of former President Hosni Mubarak.
</P>
<P>
The arrest of the Brotherhood’s spiritual leader, Mohammed Badie, appeared to represent a red line the police never crossed during Mubarak’s own crackdowns on the group. Taken together with the fact that the former president’s release for the first time seems conceivable, the developments offered a measure of how far and how quickly the tumult shaking Egypt in recent days and weeks has rolled back the changes brought by the revolution of 2011.
</P>
<P>
The order for Mubarak’s release, under a government led by former officials who worked for him, conjured the incongruous notion that he might go free even as his democratically elected successor, the Islamist Mohammed Morsi, remained in detention by the military that ousted him in early July and installed an interim government.
</P>
<P>
In a kind of counterpoint, the arrest of Badie showed the severity of the crackdown on Islamist forces that has left hundreds dead. A private television network that supports the military leadership broadcast footage of Badie, 70, in custody, with triumphal music playing against images of him clad in a white robe and sitting on a white couch with a security officer’s automatic rifle visible nearby.
</P>
<P>
His incarceration, which followed the death of a son, Ammar, in clashes Friday, was apparently designed to further deflate the Brotherhood’s resolve to maintain its challenge to the military-backed government with street protests clamoring for Morsi’s release.
</P>
<P>
Badie was arrested in an apartment in the northeastern Nasr City neighborhood of Cairo, news reports said, close to a mosque at the center of a six-week sit-in by Islamist supporters of Morsi at a protest camp that the security forces dispersed with gunfire and tear gas last Wednesday. Raids on that camp and another near Cairo University killed hundreds, prompting violent clashes. In recent days the protests have seemed less intense, suggesting that the Brotherhood may be retreating underground.
</P>
<P>
Its three top leaders are now in jail, along with Morsi, and after six weeks of massive protests across the country against the ouster of Morsi, demonstrations in and near the capital were becoming hard to find Tuesday.
</P>
<P>
Charged with incitement to murder, Badie and his two deputies face trial later this month.
</P>
<P>
His arrest, made known in the early hours, came as Egyptians struggled to absorb the notion that Mubarak, overthrown as a reviled despot in February 2011, might be freed. Few legal analysts thought a release was likely, at least in the coming weeks. But under the government installed last month by Gen. Abdel-Fattah el-Sissi, they say, it is no longer a foregone conclusion that prosecutors will continue to find reasons to detain Mubarak.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
